The idea for this project first arose for me about a year ago.  It was the second semester, after I had taken Introduction to Computer Science was using Mr. Dengler's Meggy Jr. to create a program that simulated civilizations on a blank 8x8 playing field called Civi.  I lamented that I could not make it more sophisticated without a more powerful computer and a higher-resolution screen.
A few weeks before the independent project was assigned, I started playing Sid Meier's Civilization V.  I noted the realistic generation of the biomes and the hexagonal tiles on the cylindrical earth, and I thought, wouldn't the game be more realistic and more interesting if it were a sphere?  Of course, hexagons do not tesselate on a spherical surface, so one would have to use curvy misshapen rectangles.  When we did PixLab in class and I finished it a few classes early, I thought it was the perfect opportunity to try to code such a spherical terrain generator.  The most difficult part was the animated graphics.  I spent about a day researching graphics jointly with Devon Lee, and it was he who eventually figured out the basics of JPanels and JFrames and sent me a sample program that drew a loading bar on the screen.  I adapted it to fit my needs and created the basics of my spherical terrain generator.  Devon Lee worked on a separate cylindrical terrain generator simultaneously.  When the time came to pick independent projects, though, I was the only one who sought to expand my terrain generator far beyond simple geology, into the realm of politics.  I sought to make my project the next generation of Civi: CiviHD!
I learned many basic facts along this path.  I had to come to a basic level of understanding with graphics and sound, with which Devon also helped me.  I had to use JPanels1, JFrames1, Graphics1, MouseListeners, and java.applet.AudioClips2.  Through experimenting with the many different display options I coded3 and some of the plateTechtonics() math4, I also learned a lot of trigonometry, like how to calculate the angle between two three-dimensional vectors given cartesian coordinates5.  I learned how to use final methods and bit shifts to optimize code, and I learned that subclasses cannot access private variables of superclasses, forcing me to make many variables public.  I also gained many java skills.  My class organization is extremely different now than I thought it would be when I set out, due to variables I needed to access, classes with too much code in them, and code I did not necessarily need to compile every time.
Naturally, there were obstacles, and things I could not get to.  rain() caused me a lot of delay, as every algorithm I tried was unsuccessful in producing the long rivers I so wanted.  The one I finally settled on was merely because I had spent so much time on rain() I was running out of time for the Civis.  On the list of things I wanted to implement but never got around to are ultra-rare robot and mermaid Civis, natural disasters like meteors and floods, the ability to save worlds to a file, the ability to customize the generation statistics of a file, an interactive interface through which the user could throw meteors at the world, and a high-quality rendering of the planet spinning, with clouds depicted during the day and city-lights depicted at night.  I may still return to these if I have free time after I turn in the project.
Despite all this, I am very happy with my final project.  It is highly advanced, and I spent a lot of time on it.  CiviHD is something I can be proud of for a long time.